<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter" n="005"><head>Chapter 5: Diagon Alley</head>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> woke early the next morning. Although he could tell it was daylight, he kept his eyes shut tight.</p>

   <p>“It was a dream,” he told himself firmly. “I dreamed a giant called <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> came to tell me I was 
      going to a school for wizards. When I open my eyes I’ll be at home in my <placeName>cupboard</placeName>.”</p>

   <p>There was suddenly a loud tapping noise.</p>
            
   <p>And there’s <persName type="muggle">Aunt Petunia</persName> knocking on the <objectName>door</objectName>, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> thought, 
      his heart sinking. But he still didn’t open his eyes. It had been such a good dream.</p>
            
   <p>Tap. Tap. Tap.</p>
            
   <p>“All right,” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> mumbled, “I’m getting up.”</p>

   <p>He sat up and <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>’s heavy <objectName>coat</objectName> fell off him. The hut was full of sunlight, the storm was over, 
      <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> himself was asleep on the collapsed <objectName>sofa</objectName>, and there was an owl rapping its claw on the <objectName>window</objectName>, 
      a <objectName>newspaper</objectName> held in its beak.</p>
            
   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> scrambled to his feet, so happy he felt as though a large <objectName>balloon</objectName> was swelling inside him. 
      He went straight to the <objectName>window</objectName> and jerked it open. The owl swooped in and dropped the <objectName>newspaper</objectName> on top of <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, 
      who didn’t wake up. The owl then fluttered onto the floor and began to attack <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>’s <objectName>coat</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Don’t do that.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> tried to wave the owl out of the way, but it snapped its beak fiercely at him and carried on 
      savaging the <objectName>coat</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“<persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>!” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> loudly. “There’s an owl —”</p>
            
   <p>“Pay him,” <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> grunted into the <objectName>sofa</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“What?”</p>

   <p>“He wants payin’ fer deliverin’ the <objectName>paper</objectName>. Look in the pockets.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>’s coat seemed to be made of nothing but pockets — bunches of <objectName>keys</objectName>, <objectName>slug pellets</objectName>, balls of <objectName>string</objectName>, 
      <objectName>peppermint humbugs</objectName>, <objectName>teabags</objectName> … finally, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> pulled out a handful of strange-looking <objectName>coins</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Give him five <objectName>Knuts</objectName>,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> sleepily.</p>

   <p>“<objectName>Knuts</objectName>?”</p>

   <p>“The little bronze ones.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> counted out five little bronze <objectName>coins</objectName>, and the owl held out his leg so 
      <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> could put the money into a small leather <objectName>pouch</objectName> tied to it. Then he flew off through the open <objectName>window</objectName>.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> yawned loudly, sat up, and stretched.</p>

   <p>“Best be off, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, lots ter do today, gotta get up ter <placeName type="city">London</placeName> an’ buy all yer stuff fer school.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> was turning over the wizard <objectName>coins</objectName> and looking at them. 
      He had just thought of something that made him feel as though the happy <objectName>balloon</objectName> inside him had got a puncture.</p>

   <p>“Um — <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>?”</p>

   <p>“Mm?” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, who was pulling on his huge <objectName>boots</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“I haven’t got any <objectName>money</objectName> — and you heard <persName type="muggle">Uncle Vernon</persName> last night … he won’t pay for me to go and learn magic.”</p>
            
   <p>“Don’t worry about that,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, standing up and scratching his head. 
      “D’yeh think yer parents didn’t leave yeh anything?”</p>

   <p>“But if their house was destroyed —”</p>

   <p>“They didn’ keep their <objectName>gold</objectName> in the house, boy! Nah, first stop fer us is <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName>. Wizards’ bank. Have a <objectName>sausage</objectName>, they’re not
      bad cold — an’ I wouldn’ say no teh a bit o’ yer birthday <objectName>cake</objectName>, neither.”</p>

   <p>“Wizards have banks?”</p>

   <p>“Just the one. <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName>. Run by goblins.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> dropped the bit of <objectName>sausage</objectName> he was holding.</p>

   <p>“Goblins?”</p>

   <p>“Yeah — so yeh’d be mad ter try an’ rob it, I’ll tell yeh that. Never mess with goblins, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>. 
      <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName> is the safest place in the world fer anything yeh want ter keep safe — ’cept maybe <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>. 
      As a matter o’ fact, I gotta visit <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName> anyway. Fer <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_headmaster">Dumbledore</persName>. <orgName type="school">Hogwarts</orgName> business.” 
      <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> drew himself up proudly. “He usually gets me ter do important stuff fer him. 
      Fetchin’ you — gettin’ things from <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName> — knows he can trust me, see.</p>

   <p>“Got everythin’? Come on, then.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> followed <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> out onto the rock. 
      The sky was quite clear now and the sea gleamed in the sunlight. The <objectName>boat</objectName> <persName type="muggle">Uncle Vernon</persName> had hired was still there, 
      with a lot of water in the bottom after the storm.</p>

   <p>“How did you get here?” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> asked, looking around for another <objectName>boat</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Flew,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Flew?”</p>

   <p>“Yeah — but we’ll go back in this. Not s’pposed ter use magic now I’ve got yeh.”</p>

   <p>They settled down in the <objectName>boat</objectName>, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> still staring at <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, 
      trying to imagine him flying.</p>

   <p>“Seems a shame ter row, though,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, giving Harry another of his sideways looks. 
      “If I was ter — er — speed things up a bit, would yeh mind not mentionin’ it at <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>?”</p>

   <p>“Of course not,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, eager to see more magic. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> 
      pulled out the pink <objectName>umbrella</objectName> again, tapped it twice on the side of the <objectName>boat</objectName>, and they sped off toward land.</p>

   <p>“Why would you be mad to try and rob <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName>?” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> asked.</p>

   <p>“Spells — enchantments,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, unfolding his <objectName>newspaper</objectName> as he spoke. “They say there’s dragons guardin’ the 
      high-security vaults. And then yeh gotta find yer way — <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName> is hundreds of miles under <placeName type="city">London</placeName>, see. Deep 
      under the <placeName>Underground</placeName>. Yeh’d die of hunger tryin’ ter get out, even if yeh did manage ter get yer hands on summat.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> sat and thought about this while <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> read his newspaper, 
      the Daily Prophet. Harry had learned from <persName type="muggle">Uncle Vernon</persName> that people liked to be left alone while they did this, 
      but it was very difficult, he’d never had so many questions in his life.</p>

   <p>“<orgName type="government">Ministry o’ Magic</orgName> messin’ things up as usual,” <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> muttered, turning the page.</p>

   <p>“There’s a <orgName type="government">Ministry of Magic</orgName>?” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> asked, before he could stop himself.</p>

   <p>“ ’Course,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>. “They wanted <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_headmaster">Dumbledore</persName> fer Minister, o’ course, 
      but he’d never leave <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>, so old <persName type="wizard" subtype="Minister_of_Magic">Cornelius Fudge</persName> got the job.
      Bungler if ever there was one. So he pelts <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_headmaster">Dumbledore</persName> with owls every morning, askin’ fer advice.”</p>

   <p>“But what does a <orgName type="government">Ministry of Magic</orgName> do?”</p>

   <p>“Well, their main job is to keep it from the Muggles that there’s still witches an’ wizards up an’ down the country.”</p>
            
   <p>“Why?”</p>

   <p>“Why? Blimey, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, everyone’d be wantin’ magic solutions to their problems. Nah, we’re best left alone.”</p>

   <p>At this moment the <objectName>boat</objectName> bumped gently into the harbor wall. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> folded up his newspaper, and they clambered
      up the stone <objectName>steps</objectName> onto the street.</p>

   <p>Passersby stared a lot at <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> as they walked through the little town to the station. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> 
      couldn’t blame them. Not only was <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> twice as tall as anyone else, he kept pointing at 
      perfectly ordinary things like <objectName>parking meters</objectName> and saying loudly, “See that, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>? 
      Things these Muggles dream up, eh?”</p>

   <p>“<persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, panting a bit as he ran to keep up, 
      “did you say there are dragons at <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName>?”</p>

   <p>“Well, so they say,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>. “Crikey, I’d like a dragon.”</p>

   <p>“You’d like one?”</p>

   <p>“Wanted one ever since I was a kid — here we go.”</p>
            
   <p>They had reached the station. There was a train to <placeName type="city">London</placeName> in five minutes’ time. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, who didn’t understand 
      “Muggle <objectName>money</objectName>,” as he called it, gave the <objectName>bills</objectName> to <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> so he could buy their <objectName>tickets</objectName>.</p>

   <p>People stared more than ever on the train. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> took up two seats and sat knitting what looked like a canary-yellow 
      <objectName>circus tent</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Still got yer <objectName>letter</objectName>, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>?” he asked as he counted <objectName>stitches</objectName>.</p>
            
   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> took the parchment <objectName>envelope</objectName> out of his pocket.</p>

   <p>“Good,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>. “There’s a list there of everything yeh need.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> unfolded a second piece of <objectName>paper</objectName> he hadn’t noticed the night before, and read:</p>

         <fw><orgName type="school">HOGWARTS SCHOOL of WITCHCRAFT and WIZARDRY</orgName></fw>

            <fw>UNIFORM</fw>

            <p>First-year students will require:</p>

            <list>
               
            <item>1. Three sets of plain work <objectName>robes</objectName> (black)</item>

            <item>2. One plain pointed <objectName>hat</objectName> (black) for day wear</item>

            <item>3. One pair of protective <objectName>gloves</objectName> (dragon hide or similar)</item>
   
            <item>4. One winter <objectName>cloak</objectName> (black, silver fastenings)</item>

            </list>

            <p>Please note that all pupils’ <objectName>clothes</objectName> should carry <objectName>name tags</objectName></p>

            <fw>COURSE <objectName>BOOKS</objectName></fw>

            <p>All students should have a copy of each of the following:</p>

            <list>

            <item><title>The Standard Book of Spells (Grade 1)</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Miranda Goshawk</persName></item>

            <item><title>A History of Magic</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Bathilda Bagshot</persName></item>

            <item><title>Magical Theory</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Adalbert Waffling</persName></item>

            <item><title>A Beginners’ Guide to Transfiguration</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Emeric Switch</persName></item>

            <item><title>One Thousand Magical Herbs and Fungi</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Phyllida Spore</persName></item>
   
            <item><title>Magical Drafts and Potions</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Arsenius Jigger</persName></item>

            <item><title>Fantastic Beasts and Where to Find Them</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Newt Scamander</persName></item>

            <item><title>The Dark Forces: A Guide to Self-Protection</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Quentin Trimble</persName></item>

            </list>

            <fw>OTHER EQUIPMENT</fw>

            <list>
            
            <item>1 <objectName>wand</objectName></item>

            <item>1 <objectName>cauldron</objectName> (pewter, standard size 2)</item>

            <item>1 set glass or crystal <objectName>phials</objectName></item>

            <item>1 <objectName>telescope</objectName></item>

            <item>1 set <objectName>brass scales</objectName></item>

            <item>Students may also bring an owl OR a cat OR a toad</item>
            
            </list>

            <p>PARENTS ARE REMINDED THAT FIRST YEARS ARE NOT ALLOWED THEIR OWN <objectName>BROOMSTICKS</objectName></p>



   <p>“Can we buy all this in <placeName type="city">London</placeName>?” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> wondered aloud.</p>

   <p>“If yeh know where to go,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> had never been to <placeName type="city">London</placeName> before. Although <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> seemed to know 
      where he was going, he was obviously not used to getting there in an ordinary way. He got stuck in the <objectName>ticket barrier</objectName> on the <placeName>Underground</placeName>, 
      and complained loudly that the <objectName>seats</objectName> were too small and the trains too slow.</p>

   <p>“I don’t know how the Muggles manage without magic,” he said as they climbed a broken-down <objectName>escalator</objectName> that led up
      to a bustling road lined with shops.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> was so huge that he parted the crowd easily; all <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> had to do was 
      keep close behind him. They passed book shops and music stores, hamburger restaurants and cinemas, but nowhere that looked as if it could sell you
      a <objectName>magic wand</objectName>. This was just an ordinary street full of ordinary people. Could there really be piles of wizard <objectName>gold</objectName> 
      buried miles beneath them? Were there really shops that sold <objectName>spell books</objectName> and <objectName>broomsticks</objectName>? Might this not all be some 
      huge joke that the <orgName type="family">Dursleys</orgName> had cooked up? If <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> hadn’t known that the <orgName type="family">Dursleys</orgName> had no sense of humor, 
      he might have thought so; yet somehow, even though everything <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> had told him so far was unbelievable, 
      <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> couldn’t help trusting him.</p>

   <p>“This is it,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, coming to a halt, “the <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName>. It’s a famous place.”</p>

   <p>It was a tiny, grubby-looking pub. If <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> hadn’t pointed it out, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> 
      wouldn’t have noticed it was there. The people hurrying by didn’t glance at it. Their eyes slid from the big book shop on one side to the 
      record shop on the other as if they couldn’t see the <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName> at all. In fact, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> had the most 
      peculiar feeling that only he and <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> could see it. Before he could mention this, 
      <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> had steered him inside.</p>

   <p>For a famous place, it was very dark and shabby. A few old women were sitting in a corner, drinking tiny <objectName>glasses</objectName> of <objectName>sherry</objectName>. 
      One of them was smoking a long <objectName>pipe</objectName>. A little man in a top hat was talking to the old bartender, who was quite bald and looked 
      like a toothless walnut. The low buzz of chatter stopped when they walked in. Everyone seemed to know <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>; 
      they waved and smiled at him, and the bartender reached for a <objectName>glass</objectName>, saying, “The usual, <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>?”</p>

   <p>“Can’t, <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Tom</persName>, I’m on <orgName type="school">Hogwarts</orgName> business,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, 
      clapping his great hand on <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s shoulder and making <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s knees buckle.</p>

   <p>“Good Lord,” said the bartender, peering at <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, “is this — can this be — ?”</p>

   <p>The <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName> had suddenly gone completely still and silent.</p>

   <p>“Bless my soul,” whispered the old bartender, “<persName type="wizard">Harry Potter</persName> … what an honor.”</p>

   <p>He hurried out from behind the bar, rushed toward <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> and seized his hand, tears in his eyes.</p>

   <p>“Welcome back, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>, welcome back.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> didn’t know what to say. Everyone was looking at him. The old woman with the <objectName>pipe</objectName> was puffing on it 
      without realizing it had gone out. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> was beaming.</p>

   <p>Then there was a great scraping of <objectName>chairs</objectName> and the next moment, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> found himself shaking hands with everyone in the 
      <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName>.</p>

   <p>“<persName type="wizard">Doris Crockford</persName>, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>, can’t believe I’m meeting you at last.”</p>

   <p>“So proud, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>, I’m just so proud.”</p>

   <p>“Always wanted to shake your hand — I’m all of a flutter.”</p>

   <p>“Delighted, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>, just can’t tell you, <persName type="wizard">Diggle</persName>’s the name, 
      <persName type="wizard">Dedalus Diggle</persName>.”</p>

   <p>“I’ve seen you before!” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, as <persName type="wizard">Dedalus Diggle</persName>’s top <objectName>hat</objectName> 
      fell off in his excitement. “You bowed to me once in a shop.”</p>

   <p>“He remembers!” cried <persName type="wizard">Dedalus Diggle</persName>, looking around at everyone. “Did you hear that? He remembers me!”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> shook hands again and again — <persName type="wizard">Doris Crockford</persName> kept coming back for more.</p>

   <p>A pale young man made his way forward, very nervously. One of his eyes was twitching.</p>

   <p>“Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName>!” said 
      <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>. “<persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, 
      Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName> 
      will be one of your teachers at <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>.”</p>

   <p>“P-P-<persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>,” stammered Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName>, 
      grasping <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s hand, “c-can’t t-tell you how p-pleased I am to meet you.”</p>

   <p>“What sort of magic do you teach, Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName>?”</p>

   <p>“D-Defense Against the D-D-Dark Arts,” muttered Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName>, as though he’d rather not think about it. 
      “N-not that you n-need it, eh, P-P-<persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>?” He laughed nervously. “You’ll be g-getting all your <objectName>equipment</objectName>, I suppose? 
      I’ve g-got to p-pick up a new b-<objectName>book</objectName> on vampires, m-myself.” He looked terrified at the very thought.</p>

   <p>But the others wouldn’t let Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName> keep <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> to himself. It took almost ten minutes 
      to get away from them all. At last, <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> managed to make himself heard over the babble.</p>

   <p>“Must get on — lots ter buy. Come on, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Doris Crockford</persName> shook <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s hand one last time, and <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> led them through the 
      bar and out into a small, walled courtyard, where there was nothing but a <objectName>trash can</objectName> and a few weeds.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> grinned at <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Told yeh, didn’t I? Told yeh you was famous. Even Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName> was tremblin’ ter meet yeh — mind you, 
      he’s usually tremblin’.”</p>

   <p>“Is he always that nervous?”</p>

   <p>“Oh, yeah. Poor bloke. Brilliant mind. He was fine while he was studyin’ outta <objectName>books</objectName> but then he took a year off ter get some 
      firsthand experience. … They say he met vampires in the <placeName>Black Forest</placeName>, and there was a nasty bit o’ trouble with a hag — 
      never been the same since. Scared of the students, scared of his own subject — now, where’s me <objectName>umbrella</objectName>?”</p>

   <p>Vampires? Hags? <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s head was swimming. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, meanwhile, was counting bricks in the wall above 
      the <objectName>trash can</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Three up … two across …” he muttered. “Right, stand back, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.”</p>

   <p>He tapped the wall three times with the point of his <objectName>umbrella</objectName>.</p>

   <p>The <objectName>brick</objectName> he had touched quivered — it wriggled — in the middle, a small hole appeared — it grew wider and wider — a second later
      they were facing an <objectName>archway</objectName> large enough even for <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, an <objectName>archway</objectName> onto a cobbled street that twisted and 
      turned out of sight.</p>

   <p>“Welcome,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, “to <placeName>Diagon Alley</placeName>.”</p>

   <p>He grinned at <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s amazement. They stepped through the archway. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> looked quickly over his shoulder 
      and saw the <objectName>archway</objectName> shrink instantly back into solid wall.</p>

   <p>The sun shone brightly on a stack of <objectName>cauldrons</objectName> outside the nearest shop. <objectName>Cauldrons</objectName> — All Sizes — Copper, Brass, Pewter, Silver — 
      Self-Stirring — Collapsible, said a <objectName>sign</objectName> hanging over them.</p>

   <p>“Yeah, you’ll be needin’ one,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, “but we gotta get yer money first.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> wished he had about eight more eyes. He turned his head in every direction as they walked up the street, 
      trying to look at everything at once: the shops, the things outside them, the people doing their shopping. 
      A plump woman outside an <placeName type="business">Apothecary</placeName> was shaking her head as they passed, saying, “<objectName>Dragon liver</objectName>, sixteen <objectName>Sickles</objectName> an ounce, they’re mad.”</p>

   <p>A low, soft hooting came from a dark shop with a <objectName>sign</objectName> saying <placeName type="business">Eeylops Owl Emporium</placeName> — Tawny, Screech, Barn, Brown, and Snowy. 
      Several boys of about Harry’s age had their noses pressed against a <objectName>window</objectName> with <objectName>broomsticks</objectName> in it. 
      “Look,” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> heard one of them say, “the new <objectName>Nimbus Two Thousand</objectName> — fastest ever —” There were shops selling <objectName>robes</objectName>, 
      shops selling <objectName>telescopes</objectName> and strange silver <objectName>instruments</objectName> <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> had never seen before, <objectName>windows</objectName> stacked with <objectName>barrels</objectName> of <objectName>bat spleens</objectName> and <objectName>eels’ eyes</objectName>, 
      tottering <objectName>piles</objectName> of spell <objectName>books</objectName>, <objectName>quills</objectName>, and rolls of <objectName>parchment</objectName>, potion <objectName>bottles</objectName>, <objectName>globes</objectName> of the moon. …</p>

   <p>“<placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName>,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>
            
   <p>They had reached a snowy white building that towered over the other little shops. Standing beside its burnished bronze <objectName>doors</objectName>, 
      wearing a <objectName>uniform</objectName> of scarlet and gold, was —</p>

   <p>“Yeah, that’s a goblin,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> quietly as they walked up the white stone <objectName>steps</objectName> toward him. 
      The goblin was about a head shorter than <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>. He had a swarthy, clever face, a pointed beard and, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> 
      noticed, very long fingers and feet. He bowed as they walked inside. Now they were facing a second pair of <objectName>doors</objectName>, silver this time, 
      with words engraved upon them:</p>

            <lg>
         
            <l>Enter, stranger, but take heed</l>

            <l>Of what awaits the sin of greed,</l>

            <l>For those who take, but do not earn,</l>

            <l>Must pay most dearly in their turn.</l>

            <l>So if you seek beneath our floors</l>

            <l>A <objectName>treasure</objectName> that was never yours,</l>

            <l>Thief, you have been warned, beware</l>
               
            <l>Of finding more than treasure there.</l>
            
            </lg>

   <p>“Like I said, yeh’d be mad ter try an’ rob it,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>A pair of goblins bowed them through the silver <objectName>doors</objectName> and they were in a vast marble hall. About a hundred more goblins were sitting on high stools 
      behind a long counter, scribbling in large <objectName>ledgers</objectName>, weighing <objectName>coins</objectName> in brass <objectName>scales</objectName>, examining precious <objectName>stones</objectName> through <objectName>eyeglasses</objectName>. 
      There were too many doors to count leading off the hall, and yet more goblins were showing people in and out of these. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> 
      and <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> made for the counter.</p>

   <p>“Morning,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> to a free goblin. “We’ve come ter take some <objectName>money</objectName> outta Mr. <persName type="wizard">Harry Potter</persName>’s safe.”</p>

   <p>“You have his <objectName>key</objectName>, sir?”</p>

   <p>“Got it here somewhere,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, and he started emptying his pockets onto the counter, scattering a handful of 
      moldy dog <objectName>biscuits</objectName> over the goblins book of numbers. The goblin wrinkled his nose. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> watched the goblin on their right weighing 
      a pile of <objectName>rubies</objectName> as big as glowing <objectName>coals</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Got it,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> at last, holding up a tiny golden <objectName>key</objectName>.</p>

   <p>The goblin looked at it closely.</p>

   <p>“That seems to be in order.”</p>

   <p>“An’ I’ve also got a <objectName>letter</objectName> here from Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_headmaster">Dumbledore</persName>,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> importantly, 
      throwing out his chest. “It’s about the <objectName>You-Know-What</objectName> in vault seven hundred and thirteen.”</p>

   <p>The goblin read the <objectName>letter</objectName> carefully.</p>

   <p>“Very well,” he said, handing it back to <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, “I will have someone take you down to both vaults. 
      <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName>!”</p>

   <p><persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> was yet another goblin. Once <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> had crammed all the dog <objectName>biscuits</objectName> back inside his pockets, 
      he and <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> followed <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> toward one of the <objectName>doors</objectName> leading off the hall.</p>

   <p>“What’s the <objectName>You-Know-What</objectName> in vault seven hundred and thirteen?” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> asked.</p>

   <p>“Can’t tell yeh that,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> mysteriously. “Very secret. <orgName type="school">Hogwarts</orgName> business. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_headmaster">Dumbledore</persName>’s trusted me. 
      More’n my job’s worth ter tell yeh that.”</p>

   <p><persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> held the door open for them. Harry, who had expected more marble, was surprised. They were in a narrow stone passageway 
      lit with flaming torches. It sloped steeply downward and there were little railway <objectName>tracks</objectName> on the floor. <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> whistled and a 
      small <objectName>cart</objectName> came hurtling up the <objectName>tracks</objectName> toward them. They climbed in — <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> with some difficulty — and were off.</p>

   <p>At first they just hurtled through a <objectName>maze</objectName> of twisting <objectName>passages</objectName>. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> tried to remember, left, right, right, left, middle fork, 
      right, left, but it was impossible. The rattling <objectName>cart</objectName> seemed to know its own way, because <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> wasn’t steering.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s eyes stung as the cold <objectName>air</objectName> rushed past them, but he kept them wide open. Once, he thought he saw a burst of <objectName>fire</objectName> 
      at the end of a passage and twisted around to see if it was a dragon, but too late — they plunged even deeper, passing an 
      underground <objectName>lake</objectName> where huge <objectName>stalactites</objectName> and <objectName>stalagmites</objectName> grew from the ceiling and floor.</p>

   <p>“I never know,” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> called to <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> over the noise of the cart, “what’s the difference 
      between a <objectName>stalagmite</objectName> and a <objectName>stalactite</objectName>?”</p>

   <p>“<objectName>Stalagmite</objectName>’s got an ‘m’ in it,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>. “An’ don’ ask me questions just now, I think I’m gonna be sick.”</p>

   <p>He did look very green, and when the <objectName>cart</objectName> stopped at last beside a small <objectName>door</objectName> in the passage <objectName>wall</objectName>, <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> got out 
      and had to lean against the <objectName>wall</objectName> to stop his knees from trembling.</p>

   <p><persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> unlocked the <objectName>door</objectName>. A lot of green <objectName>smoke</objectName> came billowing out, and as it cleared, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> gasped. 
      Inside were mounds of gold <objectName>coins</objectName>. Columns of <objectName>silver</objectName>. Heaps of little bronze <objectName>Knuts</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“All yours,” smiled <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>All <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s — it was incredible. The <orgName type="family">Dursleys</orgName> couldn’t have known about this or they’d have had it from him faster than blinking. 
      How often had they complained how much <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> cost them to keep? And all the time there had been a small fortune belonging to him, 
      buried deep under <placeName type="city">London</placeName>.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> helped <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> pile some of it into a <objectName>bag</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“The gold ones are <objectName>Galleons</objectName>,” he explained. “Seventeen silver <objectName>Sickles</objectName> to a <objectName>Galleon</objectName> and twenty-nine <objectName>Knuts</objectName> to a <objectName>Sickle</objectName>, 
      it’s easy enough. Right, that should be enough fer a couple o’ terms, we’ll keep the rest safe for yeh.” He turned to <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName>. 
      “Vault seven hundred and thirteen now, please, and can we go more slowly?”</p>

   <p>“One speed only,” said <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName>.</p>

   <p>They were going even deeper now and gathering speed. The <objectName>air</objectName> became colder and colder as they hurtled round tight corners. 
      They went rattling over an underground ravine, and <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> leaned over the side to try to see what was down at the dark bottom, 
      but <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> groaned and pulled him back by the scruff of his neck.</p>

   <p>Vault seven hundred and thirteen had no <objectName>keyhole</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Stand back,” said <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> importantly. He stroked the <objectName>door</objectName> gently with one of his long fingers and it simply melted away.</p>
 
   <p>“If anyone but a <orgName type="business">Gringotts</orgName> goblin tried that, they’d be sucked through the <objectName>door</objectName> and trapped in there,” said <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName>.</p>

   <p>“How often do you check to see if anyone’s inside?” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> asked.</p>

   <p>“About once every ten years,” said <persName type="goblin">Griphook</persName> with a rather nasty grin.</p>
            
   <p>Something really extraordinary had to be inside this top security vault, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> was sure, and he leaned forward eagerly, 
      expecting to see fabulous <objectName>jewels</objectName> at the very least — but at first he thought it was empty. Then he noticed a grubby little <objectName>package</objectName> 
      wrapped up in brown <objectName>paper</objectName> lying on the floor. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> picked it up and tucked it deep inside his coat. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> 
      longed to know what it was, but knew better than to ask.</p>

   <p>“Come on, back in this infernal cart, and don’t talk to me on the way back, it’s best if I keep me mouth shut,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>One wild cart ride later they stood blinking in the sunlight outside <placeName type="business">Gringotts</placeName>. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> didn’t know where to run first now 
      that he had a <objectName>bag</objectName> full of <objectName>money</objectName>. He didn’t have to know how many <objectName>Galleons</objectName> there were to a <objectName>pound</objectName> to know that he was holding more <objectName>money</objectName> than he’d 
      had in his whole life — more <objectName>money</objectName> than even <persName type="muggle">Dudley</persName> had ever had.</p>

   <p>“Might as well get yer <objectName>uniform</objectName>,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, nodding toward <placeName type="business">Madam Malkin’s Robes for All Occasions</placeName>. 
      “Listen, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, would yeh mind if I slipped off fer a pick-me-up in the <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName>? I hate them <orgName type="business">Gringotts</orgName> <objectName>carts</objectName>.” 
      He did still look a bit sick, so <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> entered <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Madam Malkin</persName>’s shop alone, feeling nervous.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Madam Malkin</persName> was a squat, smiling witch dressed all in mauve.</p>

   <p>“Hogwarts, dear?” she said, when <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> started to speak. “Got the lot here — another young man being fitted up just now, 
      in fact.”</p>

   <p>In the back of the shop, a boy with a pale, pointed face was standing on a <objectName>footstool</objectName> while a second witch pinned up his long black <objectName>robes</objectName>. 
      <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Madam Malkin</persName> stood <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> on a <objectName>stool</objectName> next to him, slipped a long <objectName>robe</objectName> over his head, 
      and began to pin it to the right length.</p>

   <p>“Hello,” said the boy, “<orgName type="school">Hogwarts</orgName>, too?”</p>

   <p>“Yes,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.</p>

   <p>“My father’s next door buying my <objectName>books</objectName> and mother’s up the street looking at <objectName>wands</objectName>,” said the boy. He had a bored, drawling voice. 
      “Then I’m going to drag them off to look at racing <objectName>brooms</objectName>. I don’t see why first years can’t have their own. 
      I think I’ll bully father into getting me one and I’ll smuggle it in somehow.”</p>

   <p>Harry was strongly reminded of <persName type="muggle">Dudley</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Have you got your own <objectName>broom</objectName>?” the boy went on.</p>

   <p>“No,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Play Quidditch at all?”</p>

   <p>“No,” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> said again, wondering what on earth Quidditch could be.</p>

   <p>“I do — Father says it’s a crime if I’m not picked to play for my House, and I must say, I agree. Know what House you’ll be in yet?”</p>

   <p>“No,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, feeling more stupid by the minute.</p>

   <p>“Well, no one really knows until they get there, do they, but I know I’ll be in <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Slytherin</orgName>, all our family have been — 
      imagine being in <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Hufflepuff</orgName>, I think I’d leave, wouldn’t you?”</p>

   <p>“Mmm,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, wishing he could say something a bit more interesting.</p>

   <p>“I say, look at that man!” said the boy suddenly, nodding toward the front window. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> was standing there, 
      grinning at <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> and pointing at two large <objectName>ice cream</objectName>s to show he couldn’t come in.</p>

   <p>“That’s <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, pleased to know something the boy didn’t. “He works at <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>.”</p>

   <p>“Oh,” said the boy, “I’ve heard of him. He’s a sort of servant, isn’t he?”</p>

   <p>“He’s the gamekeeper,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>. He was liking the boy less and less every second.</p>

   <p>“Yes, exactly. I heard he’s a sort of savage — lives in a hut on the school grounds and every now and then he gets drunk, 
      tries to do magic, and ends up setting <objectName>fire</objectName> to his <objectName>bed</objectName>.”</p>

   <p>“I think he’s brilliant,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> coldly.</p>

   <p>“Do you?” said the boy, with a slight sneer. “Why is he with you? Where are your parents?”</p>

   <p>“They’re dead,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> shortly. He didn’t feel much like going into the matter with this boy.</p>

   <p>“Oh, sorry,” said the other, not sounding sorry at all. “But they were our kind, weren’t they?”</p>

   <p>“They were a witch and wizard, if that’s what you mean.”</p>

   <p>“I really don’t think they should let the other sort in, do you? They’re just not the same, they’ve never been brought up to know our ways. 
      Some of them have never even heard of <orgName type="school">Hogwarts</orgName> until they get the <objectName>letter</objectName>, imagine. I think they should keep it in the old wizarding families. 
      What’s your surname, anyway?”</p>

   <p>But before <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> could answer, <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Madam Malkin</persName> said, “That’s you done, my dear,” and <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, 
      not sorry for an excuse to stop talking to the boy, hopped down from the <objectName>footstool</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Well, I’ll see you at <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>, I suppose,” said the drawling boy.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> was rather quiet as he ate the <objectName>ice cream</objectName> <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> had bought him 
      (chocolate and raspberry with chopped <objectName>nuts</objectName>).</p>

   <p>“What’s up?” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Nothing,” <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> lied. They stopped to buy <objectName>parchment</objectName> and <objectName>quills</objectName>. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> cheered up a bit when he 
      found a <objectName>bottle</objectName> of <objectName>ink</objectName> that changed color as you wrote. When they had left the shop, he said, “<persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, what’s Quidditch?”</p>

   <p>“Blimey, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, I keep forgettin’ how little yeh know — not knowin’ about Quidditch!”</p>

   <p>“Don’t make me feel worse,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>. He told <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> about the pale boy in <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Madam Malkin</persName>’s.</p>

   <p>“— and he said people from Muggle families shouldn’t even be allowed in —”</p>

   <p>“Yer not from a Muggle family. If he’d known who yeh were — he’s grown up knowin’ yer name if his parents are wizardin’ folk. 
      You saw what everyone in the <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName> was like when they saw yeh. Anyway, what does he know about it, 
      some o’ the best I ever saw were the only ones with magic in ’em in a long line o’ Muggles — look at yer mum! Look what she had fer a sister!”</p>

   <p>“So what is Quidditch?”</p>

   <p>“It’s our sport. Wizard sport. It’s like — like soccer in the Muggle world — everyone follows Quidditch — 
      played up in the air on <objectName>broomsticks</objectName> and there’s four <objectName>balls</objectName> — sorta hard ter explain the rules.”</p>

   <p>“And what are <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Slytherin</orgName> and <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Hufflepuff</orgName>?”</p>

   <p>“School Houses. There’s four. Everyone says <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Hufflepuff</orgName> are a lot o’ duffers, but —”</p>

   <p>“I bet I’m in <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Hufflepuff</orgName>,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> gloomily.</p>

   <p>“Better <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Hufflepuff</orgName> than <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Slytherin</orgName>,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> darkly. “There’s not a single witch or wizard who went bad who wasn’t in <orgName type="Hogwarts_house">Slytherin</orgName>. 
      You-Know-Who was one.”</p>

   <p>“Vol-, sorry — You-Know-Who was at <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>?”</p>

   <p>“Years an’ years ago,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>They bought <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s school <objectName>books</objectName> in a shop called <placeName type="business">Flourish and Blotts</placeName> where the <objectName>shelves</objectName> were stacked to the ceiling with <objectName>books</objectName> as 
      large as paving <objectName>stones</objectName> bound in <objectName>leather</objectName>; <objectName>books</objectName> the size of <objectName>postage stamps</objectName> in covers of silk; <objectName>books</objectName> full of peculiar symbols and a 
      few <objectName>books</objectName> with nothing in them at all. Even <persName type="muggle">Dudley</persName>, who never read anything, would have been wild to get his hands on some of these. 
      <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> almost had to drag <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> away from <title>Curses and Counter-curses (Bewitch Your Friends and 
      Befuddle Your Enemies with the Latest Revenges: Hair Loss, Jelly-Legs, Tongue-Tying and Much, Much More)</title> by <persName type="wizard" subtype="author">Professor Vindictus Viridian</persName>.</p>

   <p>“I was trying to find out how to curse <persName type="muggle">Dudley</persName>.”</p>

   <p>“I’m not sayin’ that’s not a good idea, but yer not ter use magic in the Muggle world except in very special circumstances,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>. 
      “An’ anyway, yeh couldn’ work any of them curses yet, yeh’ll need a lot more study before yeh get ter that level.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> wouldn’t let <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> buy a solid gold <objectName>cauldron</objectName>, either (“It says pewter on yer <objectName>list</objectName>”), 
      but they got a nice set of <objectName>scales</objectName> for weighing potion <objectName>ingredients</objectName> and a collapsible brass <objectName>telescope</objectName>. Then they visited the <placeName type="business">Apothecary</placeName>, which was 
      fascinating enough to make up for its horrible smell, a mixture of bad <objectName>eggs</objectName> and rotted <objectName>cabbages</objectName>. <objectName>Barrels</objectName> of slimy stuff
      stood on the floor; <objectName>jars</objectName> of <objectName>herbs</objectName>, dried <objectName>roots</objectName>, and bright <objectName>powders</objectName> lined the <objectName>walls</objectName>; bundles of <objectName>feathers</objectName>, strings of <objectName>fangs</objectName>, 
      and snarled <objectName>claws</objectName> hung from the ceiling. While <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> asked the man behind the counter for a supply of some basic potion 
      <objectName>ingredients</objectName> for <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> himself examined silver <objectName>unicorn horns</objectName> at twenty-one <objectName>Galleons</objectName> each and minuscule, 
      glittery-black <objectName>beetle eyes</objectName> (five <objectName>Knuts</objectName> a scoop).</p>

   <p>Outside the <placeName type="business">Apothecary</placeName>, <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> checked <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s list again.</p>

   <p>“Just yer wand left — oh yeah, an’ I still haven’t got yeh a birthday present.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> felt himself go red.</p>

   <p>“You don’t have to —”</p>

   <p>“I know I don’t have to. Tell yeh what, I’ll get yer animal. Not a toad, toads went outta fashion years ago, 
      yeh’d be laughed at — an’ I don’ like cats, they make me sneeze. I’ll get yer an owl. All the kids want owls, 
      they’re dead useful, carry yer <objectName>mail</objectName> an’ everythin’.”</p>

   <p>Twenty minutes later, they left <placeName type="business">Eeylops Owl Emporium</placeName>, which had been dark and full of rustling and flickering, jewel-bright eyes. 
      <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> now carried a large cage that held a beautiful snowy owl, fast asleep with her head under her wing. 
      He couldn’t stop stammering his thanks, sounding just like Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Don’ mention it,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> gruffly. “Don’ expect you’ve had a lotta <objectName>presents</objectName> from them <orgName type="family">Dursleys</orgName>. Just <placeName type="business">Ollivanders</placeName> left now — 
      only place fer <objectName>wands</objectName>, <placeName type="business">Ollivanders</placeName>, and yeh gotta have the best <objectName>wand</objectName>.”</p>

   <p>A magic <objectName>wand</objectName> … this was what <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> had been really looking forward to.</p>

   <p>The last shop was narrow and shabby. Peeling gold letters over the door read <placeName type="business">Ollivanders</placeName>: Makers of Fine <objectName>Wands</objectName> since 382b.c. 
      A single <objectName>wand</objectName> lay on a faded purple <objectName>cushion</objectName> in the dusty <objectName>window</objectName>.</p>

   <p>A tinkling <objectName>bell</objectName> rang somewhere in the depths of the shop as they stepped inside. It was a tiny place, empty except for a single, 
      spindly <objectName>chair</objectName> that <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> sat on to wait. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> felt strangely as though he had entered a very strict library; 
      he swallowed a lot of new questions that had just occurred to him and looked instead at the thousands of narrow <objectName>boxes</objectName> piled neatly right up 
      to the ceiling. For some reason, the back of his neck prickled. The very <objectName>dust</objectName> and silence in here seemed to tingle with some secret magic.</p>

   <p>“Good afternoon,” said a soft voice. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> jumped. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> must have jumped, too, because there was a 
      loud crunching noise and he got quickly off the spindly <objectName>chair</objectName>.</p>

   <p>An old man was standing before them, his wide, pale eyes shining like moons through the gloom of the shop.</p>

   <p>“Hello,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> awkwardly.</p>

   <p>“Ah yes,” said the man. “Yes, yes. I thought I’d be seeing you soon. <persName type="wizard">Harry Potter</persName>.” It wasn’t a question. “You have your mother’s eyes. 
      It seems only yesterday she was in here herself, buying her first <objectName>wand</objectName>. Ten and a quarter inches long, swishy, made of willow. 
      Nice <objectName>wand</objectName> for charm work.”</p>

   <p>Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> moved closer to <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> wished he would blink. 
      Those silvery eyes were a bit creepy.</p>

   <p>“Your father, on the other hand, favored a mahogany <objectName>wand</objectName>. Eleven inches. Pliable. A little more power and excellent for transfiguration. 
      Well, I say your father favored it — it’s really the <objectName>wand</objectName> that chooses the wizard, of course.”</p>

   <p>Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> had come so close that he and <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> were almost nose to nose. 
      <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> could see himself reflected in those misty eyes.</p>

   <p>“And that’s where …”</p>

   <p>Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> touched the lightning scar on <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s forehead with a long, white finger.</p>

   <p>“I’m sorry to say I sold the <objectName>wand</objectName> that did it,” he said softly. “Thirteen-and-a-half inches. Yew. Powerful <objectName>wand</objectName>, very powerful, 
      and in the wrong hands … well, if I’d known what that <objectName>wand</objectName> was going out into the world to do. …”</p>

   <p>He shook his head and then, to <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s relief, spotted Hagrid.</p>

   <p>“<persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Rubeus</persName>! <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Rubeus Hagrid</persName>! How nice to see you again. … Oak, sixteen inches, rather bendy, wasn’t it?”</p>

   <p>“It was, sir, yes,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Good <objectName>wand</objectName>, that one. But I suppose they snapped it in half when you got expelled?” said Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName>, suddenly stern.</p>

   <p>“Er — yes, they did, yes,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>, shuffling his feet. “I’ve still got the <objectName>pieces</objectName>, though,” he added brightly.</p>

   <p>“But you don’t use them?” said Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> sharply.</p>

   <p>“Oh, no, sir,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> quickly. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> noticed he gripped his pink <objectName>umbrella</objectName> very tightly as he spoke.</p>

   <p>“Hmmm,” said Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName>, giving <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> a piercing look. “Well, now — Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>. 
      Let me see.” He pulled a long <objectName>tape measure</objectName> with silver markings out of his pocket. “Which is your <objectName>wand</objectName> arm?”</p>

   <p>“Er — well, I’m right-handed,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.</p>

   <p>“Hold out your arm. That’s it.” He measured <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> from shoulder to finger, then wrist to elbow, shoulder to floor, 
      knee to armpit and round his head. As he measured, he said, “Every <orgName type="business">Ollivander</orgName> wand has a core of a powerful magical substance, 
      Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>. We use <objectName>unicorn hairs</objectName>, <objectName>phoenix tail feathers</objectName>, and the <objectName>heartstrings of dragons</objectName>. No two <orgName type="business">Ollivander</orgName> 
      <objectName>wands</objectName> are the same, just as no two unicorns, dragons, or phoenixes are quite the same. And of course, you will never get such 
      good results with another wizard’s <objectName>wand</objectName>.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> suddenly realized that the <objectName>tape measure</objectName>, which was measuring between his nostrils, was doing this on its own. 
      Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> was flitting around the <objectName>shelves</objectName>, taking down <objectName>boxes</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“That will do,” he said, and the <objectName>tape measure</objectName> crumpled into a heap on the floor. “Right then, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>. Try this one. 
      Beech-wood and <objectName>dragon heartstring</objectName>. Nine inches. Nice and flexible. Just take it and give it a wave.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> took the <objectName>wand</objectName> and (feeling foolish) waved it around a bit, but Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> snatched it out of 
      his hand almost at once.</p>

   <p>“Maple and <objectName>phoenix feather</objectName>. Seven inches. Quite whippy. Try —”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> tried — but he had hardly raised the <objectName>wand</objectName> when it, too, was snatched back by Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName>.</p>

   <p>“No, no — here, ebony and <objectName>unicorn hair</objectName>, eight and a half inches, springy. Go on, go on, try it out.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> tried. And tried. He had no idea what Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> was waiting for. 
      The pile of tried <objectName>wands</objectName> was mounting higher and higher on the spindly <objectName>chair</objectName>, but the more <objectName>wands</objectName> Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> 
      pulled from the <objectName>shelves</objectName>, the happier he seemed to become.</p>

   <p>“Tricky customer, eh? Not to worry, we’ll find the perfect match here somewhere — I wonder, now — yes, why not — 
      unusual combination — holly and <objectName>phoenix feather</objectName>, eleven inches, nice and supple.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> took the <objectName>wand</objectName>. He felt a sudden warmth in his fingers. He raised the <objectName>wand</objectName> above his head, brought it 
      swishing down through the dusty air and a stream of red and gold <objectName>sparks</objectName> shot from the end like a <objectName>firework</objectName>, 
      throwing dancing spots of light on to the <objectName>walls</objectName>. <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> whooped and clapped and Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> cried, 
      “Oh, bravo! Yes, indeed, oh, very good. Well, well, well … how curious … how very curious …”</p>

   <p>He put <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s <objectName>wand</objectName> back into its <objectName>box</objectName> and wrapped it in brown <objectName>paper</objectName>, still muttering, “Curious … curious …”</p>

   <p>“Sorry,” said <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>, “but what’s curious?”</p>

   <p>Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> fixed <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> with his pale stare.</p>

   <p>“I remember every <objectName>wand</objectName> I’ve ever sold, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>. Every single <objectName>wand</objectName>. It so happens that the phoenix whose <objectName>tail feather</objectName> 
      is in your wand, gave another <objectName>feather</objectName> — just one other. It is very curious indeed that you should be destined for this <objectName>wand</objectName> when its brother — 
      why, its brother gave you that scar.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> swallowed.</p>

   <p>“Yes, thirteen-and-a-half inches. Yew. Curious indeed how these things happen. The <objectName>wand</objectName> chooses the wizard, remember. 
      … I think we must expect great things from you, Mr. <persName type="wizard">Potter</persName>. … After all, <persName type="wizard">He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named</persName> 
      did great things — terrible, yes, but great.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> shivered. He wasn’t sure he liked Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> too much. He paid seven gold Galleons for his wand, 
      and Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> bowed them from his shop.</p>

   <p>The late afternoon sun hung low in the sky as <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> and <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> made their way back down <placeName>Diagon Alley</placeName>, 
      back through the <objectName>wall</objectName>, back through the <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName>, now empty. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> didn’t speak at all as they walked down the road; 
      he didn’t even notice how much people were gawking at them on the <placeName>Underground</placeName>, laden as they were with all their funny-shaped <objectName>packages</objectName>, 
      with the snowy owl asleep in its <objectName>cage</objectName> on <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>’s lap. Up another <objectName>escalator</objectName>, out into <placeName>Paddington station</placeName>; 
      <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> only realized where they were when <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> tapped him on the shoulder.</p>

   <p>“Got time fer a bite to eat before yer train leaves,” he said.</p>

   <p>He bought <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> a <objectName>hamburger</objectName> and they sat down on plastic seats to eat them. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> kept looking around. 
      Everything looked so strange, somehow.</p>

   <p>“You all right, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>? Yer very quiet,” said <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName>.</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> wasn’t sure he could explain. He’d just had the best birthday of his life — and yet — 
      he chewed his <objectName>hamburger</objectName>, trying to find the words.</p>

   <p>“Everyone thinks I’m special,” he said at last. “All those people in the <placeName type="business">Leaky Cauldron</placeName>, Professor <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_professor">Quirrell</persName>, 
      Mr. <persName type="wizard" subtype="business_owner">Ollivander</persName> … but I don’t know anything about magic at all. How can they expect great things? 
      I’m famous and I can’t even remember what I’m famous for. I don’t know what happened when Vol-, sorry — I mean, the night my parents died.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> leaned across the <objectName>table</objectName>. Behind the wild beard and eyebrows he wore a very kind smile.</p>

   <p>“Don’ you worry, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>. You’ll learn fast enough. Everyone starts at the beginning at Hogwarts, you’ll be just fine. 
      Just be yerself. I know it’s hard. Yeh’ve been singled out, an’ that’s always hard. But yeh’ll have a great time at Hogwarts — I did — 
      still do, ’smatter of fact.”</p>

   <p><persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> helped <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> on to the train that would take him back to the <orgName type="family">Dursleys</orgName>, 
      then handed him an <objectName>envelope</objectName>.</p>

   <p>“Yer <objectName>ticket</objectName> fer <placeName type="school">Hogwarts</placeName>,” he said. “<date>First o’ September</date> — <placeName>King’s Cross</placeName> — it’s all on yer <objectName>ticket</objectName>. Any problems with the <orgName type="family">Dursleys</orgName>, 
      send me a <objectName>letter</objectName> with yer owl, she’ll know where to find me. … See yeh soon, <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName>.”</p>

   <p>The train pulled out of the station. <persName type="wizard">Harry</persName> wanted to watch <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> until he was out of sight; 
      he rose in his <objectName>seat</objectName> and pressed his nose against the <objectName>window</objectName>, but he blinked and <persName type="wizard" subtype="Hogwarts_employee">Hagrid</persName> had gone.</p>
         
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
